while RNA editing is critical for
generating the hundreds of thousands of
proteins that keep us alive slicing
errors can lead to devastating health
problems
one example is an often fatal disease
called spinal muscular atrophy or SMA
it's the number one genetic cause of
infant death SMA is caused by too little
of a vital protein called survival of
motor neuron or SMN in the spinal cords
motor neurons too little of this protein
causes the motor neuron to die and the
muscles that control to waste away the
smn1 gene which produces the SMN protein
is missing or damaged beyond repair in
sm a patient humans have a second SMN
producing gene called smn2 but this gene
is a poor backup because it produces
very little functional SMN protein this
efficiency stems from a mistake during
RNA editing remember that's the process
of forming a coherent are any message
that removing the gibberish letters or
in trunk but what is this mistake and
how does it cause SMA
let's say the SMN gene generates are any
copies made up of introns and exons like
this
normal RNA splicing will delete the
intron the gibberish letters in blue and
leave only the exons the red letters
generating the following message draw a
big house on the corner of the wide
Street in SMA it turns out that during
RNA splicing the 7x on of smn2 is
skipped by the machinery that edits RNA
skipping of exon 7 generates a faulty
message draw a big house on the of the
wide Street just like removing word
number seven in the sentence leads to a
statement that makes no sense
removing exon 7 in the RNA results in a
defective protein remember that SMA
patients have to rely solely on the smn2
gene to produce the survival of motor
neuron protein but due to exon skipping
not enough usable protein is made to
support normal muscle development
infants born with the most severe form
of SMA often don't make it to the second
birthday but researchers have been
studying how to fix this placing problem
one solution is called knew sooner ssin
it enables SMA patients to make more SMN
protein but how new Sanderson is a short
sequence of RNA that binds just after
exon 7 in the end edited RNA message
this tiny piece of RNA prevents exon 7
from being skipped it is called an
antisense oligonucleotides or a sox10
seven is now included in the edited
already message which in turn generates
full-length functional sm and protein by
preventing exon 7 from being skipped new
Sanderson reverses symptoms and SMA
patients